Boker tov בוקר טוב Boker tov and moadei tov ומועדי טוב. u'moadei
tov. I first just want to mention for anybody that doesn't know
that our hearts go out to Rabbi Yehuda Herzl Henkin יהודה הרצל
הנקין Yehuda Herzl Henkin and Rabbanit Chana Henkin הרבנית חנה הנקין, HaRabbanit
Chana Henkin, please be quiet, that their son Eitam איתם Eitam
and
daughter-in-law
Naama נעמה—I'm Naama sorry, I'm sorry,
I'm going to start again. Anyway, for those who don't know, Rabbi
Yehuda Herzl Henkin's son and Chana Henkin's son and daughter-in-law Eitam and
Naama were murdered yesterday in Israel when they were driving in a
car shot by Palestinian terrorists. So our heart really goes out to
them and the family. And for anybody who wants to know, there's
going to be a memorial at 11:00 in front of the Palestinian
UN mission for them. So, thank you. Hamakom yenachem otam b'toch sh'ar
aveilei tziyon v'yerushalayim המקום ינחם אותם בתוך שאר אבלי ציון וירושלים. Hamakom
yenachem otam b'toch sh'ar aveilei tziyon v'yerushalayim.
Maybe appropriately today's daf דף daf deals very much with the whole
issue of death and we move on to the transition to the
third prohibition of nazir נזיר nazir from wine and shaving to that
of becoming tamei l'meitim טמא למתים. tamei l'meitim. So let's pick up
at the bottom, the Mishnah משנה Mishnah at the bottom of mem
bet amud aleph מ״ב עמוד א׳. mem bet amud aleph. Nazir shehayah
shoteh yayin kol hayom נזיר שהיה שותה יין כל היום, Nazir shehayah
shoteh yayin kol hayom, eino chayav ela achat אינו חייב אלא אחת.
eino chayav ela achat. If a nazir was drinking wine the whole
day, so he only gets one set of lashes.
It's an interesting formulation.
Some rishonim ראשונים, Rishonim, I'm trying to remember who said this, it
might be the Rosh הרא״ש, the Rosh, that said that he's like
chayav l'shamayim חייב לשמים chayav l'shamayim for every drinking that he does,
but he only gets one set of, like you know, as each
one is like as a separate prohibition, but he only gets one
set of lashes if he was only warned once. It's an interesting
question. Do you view it as multiple acts that he's just not
going to get multiple lashes because it's multiple of the same and
there's not the structure to get multiple lashes, or do you view
it as one ongoing act? But in contrast to that, amru lo
al tishteh al tishteh אמרו לו אל תשתה אל תשתה, amru lo
al tishteh al tishteh, if they said to him don't drink, don't
drink, so they warned him before each drinking, vehu shoteh והוא שותה
v'hu shoteh and he drank each time, chayav al kol achat v'achat
חייב על כל אחת ואחת, chayav al kol achat v'achat, then the
warning itself is sufficient basis for labeling it a separate prohibition, a
separate violation, maybe a separate act, presumably even if the drinking was
done toch k'dei shtiyat revi'it תוך כדי שתיית רביעית. toch k'dei shtiyat
revi'it. So as he was drinking, you know, those could have been
drinkings that could have halakhically הלכתית halakhically combined to be defined as
one drinking, presumably the act of warning defines those as not only
as separate violations, but also as separate acts. Okay. So and on
the other hand, if he drank once in the morning and one
wonders what, you know, later in the day, maybe even three days
later, if it's not coming with a separate warning, now if he
drinks three days later those clearly are separate acts, but you can't
get a separate set of lashes without a separate warning. So it
is interesting here whether the, you know, on the one hand with
the warnings, that's enough, that presumably is enough to define and to
divide those things as separate acts even if they were within a
short period of time. And on the other hand, that's presumably the
case. In the absence of the warnings, even though they're clearly separate
acts, you do not get a separate set of lashes because there
is only one hatra'ah התראה. hatra'ah. Yes.
And what if
there's a hatra'ah she-hi achat התראה שהיא אחת? hatra'ah she-hi achat? He
pulled two hairs and then...
Well,
we're going to do that, that's the next line in the Mishnah.
But also presumably this would be the same. In other words, we
said there are separate lavin לאוין, lavin, so if they said if
you were drinking wine and also eating grapes, there are three separate
malkot מלכות? malkot?
Right, but they'd have to give him separate warnings. Oh, but he
could do but if he did that all b'vat achat בבת אחת
b'vat achat he'd still get three sets and that came up earlier
in the Gemara גמרא.
Gemara. It could be different warnings, right? You could say please don't
drink, don't eat grapes.
Right. It could be one sentence, but each one has to be
labeled separately. But yes, that we discussed earlier. It could also... so
if you have separate warnings and they're separate lavin לאוין, lavin, then
even taking place at the same time is separate sets of lashes.
Now, hayah m'galeach kol hayom היה מגלח כל היום, hayah m'galeach kol
hayom, he was spending the whole day getting a haircut, eino chayav
ela achat אינו חייב אלא אחת. eino chayav ela achat. He only
actually gets one set of lashes. It's an interesting formulation. Some rishonim
ראשונים, Rishonim, I'm trying to remember who said this, it might be
that he said he was using a razor. We had that whole
discussion. Okay, misparayim k'ein ta'ar מספרים כעין תער. misparayim k'ein ta'ar. Anyway,
only gets one set of lashes. Amru lo al tiglach al tiglach
אמרו לו אל תגלח אל תגלח. amru lo al tiglach al tiglach.
They said before he cut each hair before we said that even
a single hair was chayav חייב chayav at least according to Tosafot's
reading תוספות, Tosafot, then chayav al kol achat v'achat חייב על כל
אחת ואחת, chayav al kol achat v'achat, he gets a separate set
of lashes. So that's a case where it's the same prohibition done
multiple times or some cases maybe one long prohibition and only with
the separate warnings would you get a separate set of lashes. Amru
lo al titamei al titamei hayah mitamei l'meitim kol hayom אמרו לו
אל תטמא אל תטמא היה מיטמא למתים כל היום. amru lo al
titamei al titamei hayah mitamei l'meitim kol hayom. He was coming in
contact with the dead all day. Eino chayav ela achat אינו חייב
אלא אחת. eino chayav ela achat. He only is one. Amru lo
al titamei al titamei אמרו לו אל תטמא אל תטמא, amru lo
al titamei al titamei, do not become, don't, don't become tamei טמא,
tamei, don't become tamei טמא, tamei, vehu mitamei והוא מיטמא, v'hu mitamei,
and he is becoming tamei טמא, tamei, chayav al kol achat v'achat
חייב על כל אחת ואחת, chayav al kol achat v'achat, he's chayav
חייב chayav for every separate one. Now I do think that although
these are all parallel, first of all I should say that the
Gemara גמרא Gemara is going to sort of ignore the basic point
of the Mishnah משנה, Mishnah, which is how... How the התראה hatra'ah
is necessary and also functions to separate the acts, and is going
to hone in on the issue of מטמא למתים, mitamei le-meisim, which
is the third prohibition of נזיר nazir that we have not been
focusing on. Now before we do that I suggest saying that a
priori here you could think about טומאה tumah could be better or
worse in terms of thinking about it as multiple transgressions. On the
one hand something like getting a haircut or eating can be seen
as process, as a process that begins and takes place over time
and easier to see multiple things as not separate haircuts but as
you know the ongoing single haircut or you're just drinking all day
you know how much do we conceptualize it as one process whereas
being מטמא למתים mitamei le-meisim that's not a process of being מטמא
למתים mitamei le-meisim I mean you know I guess you could say
somebody's in the process of burying his relative but in terms of
thinking about the act of becoming טמא tamei each one almost by
definition is a separate act we're not dealing with a process so
that's on the one hand a reason to think that they're more
separate and maybe again the הלכה halachah is the same but maybe
a little bit of more a priori reason to consider it a
separate act on the other hand and this is what the גמרא
Gemara is going to focus on and this is going to be
a critical גמרא Gemara not for נזיר nazir but for כהנים kohanim
is the issue that once a person already becomes טמא tamei what
is the significance of touching another dead body meaning if I go
ahead and I drink more wine more of the prohibited substance has
entered into my body okay if I go ahead and cut another
hair I've actually removed another hair from my head I've actually done
something more than I did before okay but טומאה tumah is not
just the touching of the dead body presumably it's the communicating of
the impurity that comes as a result of touching that dead body
and if I touch on the same day like if I touch
tomorrow so then my טומאה tumah has gone conceptually you could argue
has gone down a little cause now I only have two days
before they can sprinkle the ashes of the פרה אדומה parah adumah
rather than three
it's not three days is it from when you first become טמא
tamei
no if I touched on Sunday they sprinkle the ashes of the
פרה אדומה parah adumah on Tuesday okay but if I but if
I waited till Monday and touched again so when I was at
Monday I only had one day to go till the ashes and
now I touched again I have two days to go till the
ashes is that clear why why does that mean if I touch
a dead body on Sunday they're going to sprinkle the ashes on
me on Tuesday it will be the first sprinkling it's day three
and day seven right okay let's say on on I wait on
Monday I touch another dead body then that actually has some real
world impact that means that I have to wait another day before
the ashes but if I touch another dead body on Sunday there's
no impact I'm already טמא tamei so what did I do I
touched a dead body but did I do another act of becoming
טמא tamei that is the serious question the גמרא Gemara is going
to ask and that's going to focus us on the relevant question
about whether כהנים kohanim are prohibited to the nature of the prohibition
nowadays if we assume for example that all כהנים kohanim are טמא
tamei to become טמא tamei once you're already טמא tamei okay so
okay so we will so this is like the central גמרא Gemara
for that question yes Tovi you have a question
why is it not in what way is it not like taking
another sip of wine
because when you take another sip of wine more prohibited liquid has
entered into your body
so the contact with a prohibited corpse has
happened again so if the Torah said right so if we conceptualize
it as a prohibition of touching a dead body if that's the
prohibition of touching a dead body then you're right then you did
it again you did the prohibited act again but if the prohibition
is becoming
טמא tamei through right through contact of a dead body it says
על כל נפש מת לא יבוא al kol nefesh meis lo yavo
so that actually speaks about the act but what's the other prohibition
what does it say it says you can look at the פסוק
pasuk but if we conceptualize the prohibition as becoming טמא tamei through
contact or any encounter carrying אוהל ohel whatever with a dead body
then it's achieving that state then you haven't re-achieved that state I
mean that state was already there so that would be the conceptual
difference okay
yes if somebody becomes טמא tamei from a dead body say very
close to nightfall or something yeah and he could be sprinkled the
first thing in the morning Tuesday does he have to wait
no it's not 72 hours it's the third day yeah okay איתמר
itmar so let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara is
that transfer to אוהל ohel if it's transfer to a building
yeah well so that's exactly what we're going to take a look
at dead body okay so let's take a look it's going to
be the first line of the גמרא Gemara yeah yeah yeah איתמר
itmar yes אמר רבה אמר רב הונא amar Rabbah amar Rav Huna
מקרא מלא דיבר כתוב mikra malei diber kasuv
the Torah speaks fully which is an interesting way to say it
okay but basically meaning that there are two prohibitions that were explicit
לא יטמא lo yitama it already said לא יטמא lo yitama
so what does it what's the פסוק pasuk Michael there לאביו ולאמו
לא יטמא l'aviv u'l'imo lo yitama right so על נפש מת לא
יבוא al kol nefesh meis lo yavo לאביו ולאמו
לא יטמא
l'aviv
u'l'imo
lo yitama לא יטמא להם במותם lo yitama l'hem b'mosam
so that לא יטמא lo yitama means the state of becoming טמא
tamei right so it already said לא יטמא lo yitama so why
do you need to say לא יבוא lo yavo כשהוא. k'she-hu. כשהוא
אומר K'shehu omer לא יבא, lo yavo, so what's the extra לא
יבא lo yavo by a נזיר? nazir? Do not enter into the
same, under the same roof? להזהיר על הטומאה להזהיר על הביאה. L'hazhir
al hatumah l'hazhir al habiah. That is to prohibit two separate prohibitions.
One is becoming טמא, tamei, the other is entering under the same
roof. So therefore, if somebody were about to enter, I'm going to
just read this תוספות. Tosfos. If somebody were about to enter into
a house with a dead body, a נזיר, nazir, and you said,
"Don't enter in. You will be transgress entering a house and you
will transgress becoming טמא." tamei. And he said, "I don't care," and
he stepped in, he'd get two sets of lashes. Because the act
of becoming טמא tamei and the act of entering into a house
are conceptually different לאוין lavin and he would get two sets of
lashes. If he just touched a dead body, he would only get
one. If he... there's no way to enter into the house not
to transgress both sets of לאוין lavin and therefore when he enters
into the house he has transgressed both. And if he got both
warnings he gets two sets of lashes. So, so רבא Rava said
in that case those are separate prohibitions and I can imagine a
person getting both sets of, both sets of lashes.
אבל טומאה וטומאה לא. Aval tumah v'tumah lo. But if somebody basically
was טמא tamei and touched, either touched two dead bodies at once,
okay, that's just doing one לאו lav at the same time, so
obviously you only get one set of lashes. But even if he
was טמא tamei and then removed and then touched again, what the
משנה Mishnah seems to say, he says you're not going to get
another set of lashes. You're already טמא tamei and presumably the fact
that the פסוק pasuk doesn't say, "Don't touch," it says לא יטמא.
lo yitama. So when we're focusing on לא יטמא, lo yitama, if
you're already טמא, tamei, you're not going to get another set of
lashes for becoming טמא tamei again. What he does with the משנה
Mishnah we will worry about, but that's what רבא Rava said.
רב יוסף אמר חי אלוקים, Rav Yosef amar hai elokim, in God,
by God's name! אמר רב הונא. Amar Rav Huna. רב הונא Rav
Huna said because רבא Rava said that in the name of רב
הונא. Rav Huna. אפילו טומאה וטומאה, Afilu tumah v'tumah, even if you
were טמא tamei and then became טמא tamei again. And you would
and even, he's going to go even further, even if you were
still in contact with the first body and then you touched a
second body. Okay, as long as it was a separate act and
you got a separate set, you would get a separate set of
lashes. Let's say, let's imagine a parallel case, I don't know, here
I am, you say, "Don't drink," and I'm drinking, or I'd say
here, there's an easier case, a haircut. "Don't get a haircut." And
I say, "I don't care. I'm going to get a haircut." And
I'm cutting this hair, these hairs from my head. And then you
see I'm about to use my other hand to cut these hairs
and you say, "Don't get a haircut." And I say, "I don't
care," and I'm cutting these hairs, right? So, right, would you say
that there I get two sets of lashes? Even if I'm in
the process of doing this? Right? I don't know, it's an interesting
question. Anyway, this is a separate act with a separate warning, maybe
even at the same time. So רב יוסף Rav Yosef says that
I don't care, even at the same time you're already טמא, tamei,
you're still touching dead body one, you go ahead and you touch
dead body number two, that's a separate act of טומאה tumah and
if you got a separate warning, you get a separate set of
lashes. Okay, you're doing the same act twice, but you got a
separate warning, separate set of lashes. Like we would say presumably by
eating and by getting a haircut. Wait, wait, let's, let's read a
little. Let's read a little. אפילו טומאה וטומאה דאמר רב הונא נזיר
שהיה עומד בבית הקברות. Afilu tumah v'tumah d'amar Rav Huna nazir shehaya
omeid b'veit hakvarot. A נזיר nazir was standing there in the cemetery.
והושיטו לו מתו. V'hoshitu lo meito. And they handed him his dead,
you know, his like a relative of his that he was burying.
Now that's interesting because when you're dealing with a כהן, kohen, that's
permissible, right? To bury an immediate relative. By a נזיר, nazir, נזיר
nazir is like a כהן גדול kohen gadol that it's not permissible.
So really it doesn't matter whether it's his relative or not, they're
equally forbidden, but it's sort of talking about a common scenario. ומת
אחר ונגע בו. U-meit acher v'naga bo. And let's say his relative,
another, another corpse, okay, and he touch it. Even while he's still
standing in the cemetery and already actively טמא, tamei, חייב. chayav. He
transgresses, he gets a set, another set of lashes. Okay, so this
is the principle that רב יוסף Rav Yosef says. רבא Rava says
if you're already טמא, tamei, you do not get another set of
lashes. Now does רבא Rava say even the next day? Even if
you're no longer touching the dead body? We're going to clarify that.
But רבא's Rava basic point is if you're already טמא tamei you
can't get another set of lashes. Why should you? You haven't done
anything that changes any state. Okay, and presumably the focus is on
becoming טמא. tamei. You're already טמא. tamei. And רב יוסף Rav Yosef
says no, if you do another act of touching with a separate
warning, even on the same day, even if you're in contact, you're
standing in the cemetery, you would still get a separate set of
lashes.
What about touching? Forget about touching the מת. meit. At least they
say you're in the cemetery, get out, no. Get out, no. Get
out, no. Right. Would that be separate sets of lashes, even he's
not touching anyone?
Presumably. I mean, yes, that's whether שהייה shehiyah and we had a
discussion earlier whether שהייה shehiyah counts. But yes, that could, that could
very well be. Okay.
Right. But that is an interesting question. לא יטמא lo yitama includes
all forms of טומאה, tumah, not just touching. Being מאהיל ma'ahil over
the מת meit includes. Let's just be clear, being in a cemetery
doesn't make you טמא. tamei. It's being under a tree that that
that the roof of the tree is, you know, sort of encompasses
you and the, and the, and the grave or standing over the
grave. Those would be the cases, okay.
Walking a road isn't a problem?
Exactly. Technically, I mean, if you can avoid all the trees and
the overhead. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay.
So the גמרא Gemara says now, so that's the debate, right? Basically,
to set more simply, if you're already טמא, tamei, do you transgress
or get lashes, which is more immediate? question by becoming טמא Tamei
again? And רב יוסף Rav Yosef says, yup, even if you're still
touching the first body. So the גמרא Gemara says אמאי, Amai, why
is that true? המיטמי וקאים, Hamitamei vekayeim, he's already טמא! Tamei! What
has he done? Right? He hasn't done anything different here again because
particularly טומאה Tumah should focus on his status. So the גמרא Gemara
says אלא לאו שמע מינה אמר רב הונא אפילו טומאה וטומאה. Ella
lav shema mina Amar Rav Huna afilu tumah ve'tumah. So actually, I'm
sorry, that was asked rhetorically, but it points out to the problem.
Why should you become get lashes? Aren't you already טמא? Tamei? So
you see that רב הונא Rav Huna says it doesn't matter. Yes,
even a טומאה Tumah that follows a טומאה, Tumah, even when you're
actively טמא, Tamei, you do get a separate set of lashes, you
did another touching of a dead body. Okay, so that's the position
of רב יוסף Rav Yosef according to רב הונא. Rav Huna. Now
we're going to see how now we're going to try to bring
proofs and primarily the proofs focus on challenging the position of רב
יוסף Rav Yosef because that seems to be stranger that even though
you're already טמא Tamei you transgress again. So let's take a look.
If you were in the hospital and even with his own relative,
a כהן Kohen with a relative, his relative died, and someone else
in the hospital died, he doesn't know about it.
Yeah, okay,
fine, that might be and then you have to worry about likelihood
and so on but those are relevant issues but we're nowhere up
to that type of a question yet. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says like this. איתיבי אביי. Eiseiv Abaye. So אביי Abaye asked רב
יוסף Rav Yosef presumably. כהן שהיו לו מת מונח על כתיפו והושיטו
לו מתו ומת אחר ונגע בו יכול יהא חייב תלמוד לומר ולא
יחלל במי שאינו מחולל יצא זה שהוא מחולל ועומד. Kohen she'hayu lo
meit munach al kteifo ve'hoshitu lo meito u'meit acher ve'nagah bo yachol
yehei chayav talmud lomar ve'lo yichalel b'mi she'eino mechulal yatza zeh she'mechulal
ve'omeid. So a כהן Kohen had a corpse on his shoulder, presumably
wasn't even a relative though he already transgressed, a מת meit but
it could be a relative or a מת מצווה, meit mitzvah, could
be he didn't transgress, could be he did transgress, that's really not
relevant, he's already טמא, Tamei, whatever was done was done, and then
they gave him another dead body. Okay, or ונגע בו, ve'nagah bo,
now of course if it was מתו, meito, if it was an
immediate relative, of course he wouldn't be חייב chayav for the second
one, but anyway, somebody that he's a non-relative,
יכול יהא חייב, yachol yehei chayav, maybe you would be transgressed, תלמוד
לומר ולא יחלל, talmud lomar ve'lo yichalel, he shall not desecrate, במי
שאינו מחולל, b'mi she'eino mechulal, somebody who's not yet desecrated,
יצא זה שהוא מחולל ועומד, yatza zeh she'u mechulal ve'omeid, which excludes
this person that their status has already been violated. Now of course
interestingly you could conceptually distinguish between a כהן Kohen and a נזיר.
Nazir. Maybe כהן Kohen it says ולא יחלל lo yichalel and this
is a relevant act and maybe נזיר Nazir not. The גמרא's Gemara
going to assume that they're all the same. Okay? So the גמרא
Gemara says look, we got a ברייתא Braita that says that a
כהן Kohen
does not transgress, doesn't get lashes. This is certainly seems that טומאה
וטומאה לא. tumah ve'tumah lo. It's a proof against רב יוסף, Rav
Yosef, at least, at least because he's already טמא, Tamei, at least
in the case of a כהן. Kohen. But again, the גמרא's Gemara
assuming כהן Kohen and נזיר Nazir are the same. So אמר ליה,
Amar leh, so רב יוסף Rav Yosef said back, ותיפשוט לך מתניתין.
ve'tivshu lach masnitin. One minute, you got a ברייתא Braita that says
you're not חייב chayav a second time. Wonderful. But how about the
משנה? Mishna? The משנה Mishna proves it like me that you are
חייב chayav a second time. דתנן היה מיטמא למתים כל היום אינו
חייב אלא אחת אמרו לו אל תטמא אל תטמא חייב על כל
אחת ואחת. Detnan hayah mitamei le'meitim kol hayom eino chayav ela achat
amru lo al teitamei al teitamei chayav al kol achat ve'achat. So
he transgresses multiple times on the same day. ואמאי המיטמי וקאי? Ve'amai
hamitamei ve'kai? Look, he's already טמא. Tamei. So you got a ברייתא
Braita that supports you, I got a משנה Mishna that supports me.
So the way תוספות Tosafot reads it, רב יוסף's Rav Yosef basic
response is reject the ברייתא. Braita. We don't פוסק pasken like the
ברייתא, Braita, fine. Again, it would also be interesting to say the
ברייתא's Braita by a כהן, Kohen, the משנה's Mishna by a נזיר,
Nazir, but okay, you can write that for your own תורה Torah
on why the גמרא Gemara didn't say that,
but רב יוסף's Rav Yosef saying forget about, maybe, maybe that's implicit
in what רב יוסף Rav Yosef says, but רב יוסף's Rav Yosef
saying forget about the ברייתא. Braita. Okay, the משנה Mishna makes it
clear that you become טמא Tamei multiple times on the same day,
you're חייב, chayav, טומאה וטומאה, tumah ve'tumah, end of story. Okay, so
let's take a look. אלא קשיא אהדדי. Ella kashya hadadi. Oh, but
okay, now they do contradict one another. What is אביי Abaye going
to say? Like this is גמרא Gemara saying it, it's like summary
that the whole thing is part of אביי's Abaye statement anyway, but
the point is the same. So okay, so now we got a
problem, how you deal with that משנה Mishna if you say טומאה
וטומאה לא, tumah ve'tumah lo, if you say you don't transgress a
second time for becoming טמא Tamei again and it does contradict the
ברייתא? Braita? לא קשיא כאן בחיבורין כאן שלא בחיבורין. Lo kashya kan
b'chiburin kan she'lo b'chiburin. Here is the difference. The difference is, I'll
read it the simple way first, anyway, the difference is the following.
Am I still touching the dead body or have I removed my
hand from the dead body? While I am still touching the dead
body, if I, when did we say, would say אביי Abaye and
רבא? Rava? When did we say that touching another dead body you're
not חייב chayav because you're already טמא Tamei when you're still in
contact with the first? That's like the ברייתא, Braita, the כהן Kohen
had the dead body on his shoulder. He was directly in contact.
When does the משנה Mishna say you are חייב? chayav? When you
actually leave the cemetery and come back or remove your hand from
the body and touch it again. Okay, that's when you are. Now,
what's the difference? If I'm touching dead body number one and touching
dead body number two is clearly a separate act, it's dead body
number two. What difference does it make if I remove my hand
and touch again? or remain touching one and touch two? Either way
we're dealing with a distinct act. So the difference is the following:
the difference is, while I am touching dead body number one, my
level of טומאה tumah *tumah* is higher. Okay, the מת meit *met*
is something called an אבי אבות הטומאה *avi avot hatumah*, a grand-daddy
of טומאה tumah *tumah*. Okay, which means because normally, the thing that's
the source of טומאה tumah, *tumah* is an אב *av* is a
and that could be if a person let's say is a זב
*zav* or woman's a נדה *niddah*, it's a seven-day טומאה tumah, *tumah*,
they're the אב הטומאה *av hatumah* or מצורע Metzora *metzora*. And then
anybody that comes in contact with that person is a ראשון *rishon*
and has a one-day טומאה tumah *tumah*. Okay, but by a מת
meit *met* it's different. By a מת meis *met*, okay, here's the
here's the person on their bed, whatever. That took off and anyway
by the מת *met*, that's an אבי אבות *avi avot*. Okay, now,
the מת *met* is not itself seven days טמא tamei *tamei*; it's
טמא tamei *tamei* for forever. So that's one of the reasons. But
the person who touches it, okay, came in contact with it, he's
an אב *av* because it's seven days. Okay, that's why this is
called an אבי אבות *avi avot*, okay, because it makes even one
degree removed remain seven days. The person that touches him is a
ראשון *rishon* and one day. Okay, that's the normal הלכה *halacha*.
Okay, but yeah, אוכלין *ochlin* the same.
But let's say while, let's say we're daisy chaining, while this guy
is touching the dead body, this person is touching this guy. Okay?
In that case, that's called טומאה בחיבורין tumah b'chiburin. *tumah bechiburin* or
if you want by another גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, דיקרב לדיקרב *dikrav ledikrav*,
somebody touching somebody who is touching the dead body and they're all
touching at the same time. In that case he is seen as
an extension of the dead body, or you can conceptualize it different
way, or you can sort of say it's like electricity, whatever it
is. And in that case טומאה tumah בחיבורין *tumah bechiburin* when it's
בחיבורין *bechiburin*, בחיבורין *bechiburin*,
בחיבורין *bechiburin*, then in that case, if it's touching and touching, in
that case, this guy is seven days. Okay, this guy gets a
higher level of טומאה tumah *tumah*. All right, that's the הלכה *halacha*
of טומאה tumah בחיבורין *tumah bechiburin* by only by a מת *met*.
All right, so it's an אבי אבות *avi avot*?
Yeah. He would be considered an אב *av*. See, that's only by
a מת *met*. Now, therefore, what the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* is saying
is, here's the difference. Yes, if I'm touching one and I touch
another, it's a separate act, but it doesn't matter, my level of
טומאה tumah *tumah* was the highest possible when I'm touching, and touching
another doesn't change my level. But as soon as I remove my
hand, my level has gone down a little bit. Because now I'm
just an אב *av*. While I was touching, I was almost like
an אבי אבות *avi avot*. While I was touching, I could make
another guy into a seven-dayer. Now that I remove my hand, I
can make another person only into a one-dayer. So therefore, he says,
does the משנה *Mishnah* says you're חייב chayav *chayav*, that's because as
soon as you remove your hand, you go down a little bit
and you do something worse to your status when you touch again.
When does the ברייתא *braita* say you're not חייב chayav *chayav* a
second time? When you're actively touching, then you haven't changed your status.
Okay, כאן בחיבורין כאן שלא בחיבורין *kan bechiburin kan shelo bechiburin*. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. וטומאה בחיבורין דאורייתא d'oraita, *vetumah
bechiburin d'oraita*? Is טומאה tumah. בחיבורין דאורייתא d'oraita. *tumah bechiburin d'oraita*? This
idea that your status goes up when you're in touch. How do
we know it's not that it's דאורייתא d'oraita *d'oraita*? אמר רב יצחק
בר יוסף אמר רב ינאי *amar Rav Yitzchak bar Yosef amar Rav
Yanai*, לא אמרו lo amru? טומאה Tumah. בחיבורין אלא לתרומה ולקדשים אבל
לנזיר ועושה פסח לא *lo amru tumah bechiburin ela letrumah ulekodashim aval
lenazir ve'oseh pesach lo*. If this guy, because they were all daisy
chaining, touching while touching, etc., and therefore he's going to be considered
seven days. So basically, if this guy comes to us and says,
שמעון Shimon, *Shimon* comes to us and says, I touched ראובן Reuven,
*Reuven* while he was touching the dead body on Sunday. And now
it's Monday or Tuesday, I'd like to go ahead and bring a
קרבן *korban* or eat some תרומה trumah *terumah*. We'll say, tough luck,
buddy, you got a seven-day טומאה Tumah *tumah*, you got to wait
seven days, you got to do ashes of פרה אדומה *parah adumah*,
you got to do the whole thing. Okay, we'll tell him he's
a seven-day he has a seven-day wait. But let's say he comes
to us in that exact scenario, I touched ראובן *Reuven* when he
was touching the dead body and today is ערב פסח *Erev Pesach*.
Okay, or I was you know
or here's another case, I was a נזיר nazir *nazir*. Okay. Did
I did I violate my נזירות *nezirut* and do I have to
start all over again? Because a נזיר Nazir *nazir* is only when
they come directly in contact with the dead body, right? If the
נזיר Nazir *nazir* came in contact with ראובן *Reuven* when he wasn't
touching the dead body, so okay, he would have טומאה Tumah *tumah*
but he wouldn't be על נפש מת לא יבא *al nefesh met
lo yavo*. He would have a one-day טומאה Tumah *tumah*. So this
guy is a נזיר Nazir, *nazir* or he has to bring his
קרבן פסח korban pesach? *korban pesach*. They would say, oh, okay, then
you really aren't seven days טמא tamei *tamei*. You're only one day
טמא tamei *tamei*. You can go to the מקוה *mikvah* and you
can go eat your קרבן פסח korban pesach *korban pesach* tonight. You
don't have to go ahead and violate your whole נזירות *nezirut*. So
even if he touched ראובן *Reuven* while ראובן *Reuven* was touching the
dead body. So what does that show you? It shows you the
whole idea that he has seven days is דרבנן d'rabbanan. *derabbanan* because
we're willing to basically ignore it when there's high consequences, when he
would have to not bring a קרבן פסח *korban pesach* and or
when he would have to violate his נזירות *nezirut*, then we say,
oh, oh, if that's the case, oh then you only have a
one-day status. Okay.
So we didn't shave
his hair then in that... right, he would not have to shave
his hair, would not have to start again,
go to
the
מקוה *mikvah* and...
So in those cases we say oh forget it it's like ראובן
wasn't touching the dead body which shows that the whole thing is
דרבנן. d'rabbanan Let's just read the answer. So the גמרא Gemara says
ואי אמרת דאורייתא, v'im amart d'oraita, if you say it's דאורייתא, d'oraita.
מאי שנא, mai shna, what's the difference? So clearly it's not דאורייתא.
d'oraita. So the גמרא, Gemara so now the question is what the
גמרא's Gemara answer is. Let's see the answer. That's a pretty darn
good proof. So you cannot say that there's a higher level touching
or not touching. So the גמרא Gemara says no, כאן בחיבורי אדם
באדם, kan b'chiburei adam b'adam, כאן בחיבורי אדם במת. kan b'chiburei adam
b'meit. Okay, now what does this answer mean? I will tell you
what תוספות Tosafot says it's mean, רמב"ם Rambam has a different view.
What תוספות Tosafot says this answer means is no. When this guy
is when it's touching a guy who's touching, he's seven days and
that would be according to this read of the גמרא Gemara even
for פסח ונזיר. pesach v'nazir. So that's דאורייתא d'oraita when it's when
it's כאן בחיבורי
אדם במת. kan b'chiburei adam b'meit. If he's touching the guy touching
the מת and he's touching the guy that's חיבורי אדם במת, chiburei
adam b'meit, right, חיבורי אדם במת, chiburei adam b'meit, he's touching him,
his טומאה Tumah. is seven days דאורייתא. d'oraita. That is דאורייתא. d'oraita.
When did we say we're willing to be מוחל mochel for a
נזיר Nazir. and a קרבן פסח? The third guy. Not, okay this
is ראובן, שמעון, Shimon for לוי. Levi. Okay for לוי, Levi, he
when he touches שמעון Shimon that's חיבורי אדם באדם. chiburei adam b'adam.
He's one step more removed. So for לוי Levi we'll say that
he also is seven days if he's you know three steps removed,
okay, but for נזיר ועושה פסח nazir v'oseh pesach we'll say only
one day.
And if he was touching יהודה?
Yehuda? No, we stopped by לוי. Levi.
Okay, so anyway, so no one becomes טמא tamei if
they're touching, if יהודה Yehuda would only be טמא tamei one day,
but לוי Levi in this case would be seven days for תרומה
trumah and one day for פסח ונזיר. pesach v'nazir. Okay, תרומה וקדשים.
trumah v'kodshim. So basically the גמרא Gemara says yes we are saying
that that's a דאורייתא d'oraita. and when you remove your hand you
lower your level. This guy becoming seven days is a דאורייתא. When
we said we're willing to sort of be מיקל meikel and acknowledge
that it's only a דרבנן d'rabbanan the weight of your טומאה Tumah.
that's for guy number three, but guy number two is always going
to be a full seven days even for תרומה even for פסח
ונזיר, pesach v'nazir, yes.
Big question. First of all, for לוי Levi in that scenario, if
he's a
כהן ונזיר וערב פסח kohen v'nazir v'erev pesach it's not a good
situation for him. Okay. Did you say anything at all about this
phrase לא אמרו? lo amru?
What do you mean לא אמרו? amru, Like right just above, two
lines above, the גמרא Gemara was אמרו, they said.
No, no, no, it's coming from a different, no, yeah, it's coming
from a totally different סוגיא. sugia. Yeah exactly, totally different context when
we're talking about there's other גמרות Gemaras like this phrase I mentioned
יקרב ולא יקרב. yikrav v'lo yikrav. There's extensive סוגיות sugias about טומאה
tumah בחיבורין. So in the context of some other discussion we had
in some other גמרא Gemara you
really is you're making this assumption out of context when there's a
whole other תורה Torah out there that is informing how you should
be applying this principle.
Right. Exactly. So the first point is it doesn't apply to פסח
ונזיר pesach v'nazir which shows you that it's דרבנן d'rabbanan. and then
the pushback is that'll be for guy number three. Guy number two
we're going to insist is דאורייתא. So when you're touching the מת
you actually have a higher level of טומאה דאורייתא tumah d'oraita than
when you remove your hand. Okay, that's basically the גמרא's Gemara answer.
I should tell you just parenthetically and don't try to crack your
head figuring out how he reads it into the גמרא Gemara that
רמב"ם Rambam reads that actually the מסקנא maskana of the גמרא Gemara
is that even this guy is דרבנן. d'rabbanan Like you know that
yeah that really you don't have a higher level when you're touching
the dead body. Okay, and nevertheless the רמב"ם Rambam still says that
you're פטור patur if you're touching one and you touch another. What?
Pashbus?
The רמב"ם Rambam for גמרא Gemara seems to conclude that לוי Levi
is דרבנן d'rabbanan. and he's דאורייתא. רמב"ם Rambam says that even שמעון
Shimon is דרבנן. de'rabanan That even שמעון we'd let him bring a
קרבן פסח you know
when they're all touching each other.
Yeah, exactly, at the same time, yeah.
You said guy number four then only be טמא tamei. one day
and if guy number five's touching
guy number, you know they'd also be one day? Yeah, yeah, the
whole magic stops after guy number three. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara, says okay, so anyway reading the גמרא Gemara, the simple way,
while you're touching the dead body you have a higher level of
טומאה, tumah so you remove your hand you touch again, that's a
different act, that רבא Rava says I will say you're חייב chayav.
for two טומאות tumas on the same day because you increased your
level. But if you're touching while you're touching you touch another one,
you haven't done anything different to your status, you are going to
not get be חייב chayav and רב יוסף Rav Yosef says even
in that case you'll be חייב. chayav Now read this way, there
would be no basis for being lenient for כהנים kohanim even if
we assume and it's a whole interesting question why the ראשונים rishonim
assume that all כהנים kohanim are טמאי מת tmei meit בזמן הזה,
b'zman hazeh, you know, I guess if you've lived long enough you've
buried a, you know, they'll assume that they would have buried a
relative. at some stage, okay, and then not been טהור tahor by
the אפר הפרה. efer haparah. Now we can say people are born
in hospitals, you know, whatever. Okay, but anyway the ראשונים Rishonim start
developing this line that all everyone's טמאי מת tamei meis בזמן הזה.
bizman hazeh. There would be no basis to be lenient because or
whatever, you know, or any mitigating factors because as soon as you
remove your hand, even on the same day, touching again is another
violation, right? So keep that in mind, that's the leniency for what?
Meaning for what?
Meaning to say, well, since a כהן kohen is anyway טמא tamei,
nowadays, it's not so bad if he becomes טמא tamei again. Okay,
there would be no basis of saying that. The גמרא Gemara, says
you get another set of lashes even according to the more lenient
position of רבא, Rava, you get another set of lashes when you
remove your hand and touch again. And רב יוסף Rav Yosef says
even if you're actively touching you get another set of lashes. Okay,
so that's the simple sense of the גמרא, Gemara that's the consensus.
I want to read a little bit more and then I want
to tell you about the position of the ראב״ד. Raavad. Okay, so
let's take a look.
Okay, so that's כאן בחיבור אדם באדם כאן בחיבור אדם במת. kan
bechibur adam be'adam kan bechibur adam bemeis. אבל טומאה בטומאה לא. aval
tumah betumah lo. But if you're actively touching and you touch again,
you would not get another set of lashes. טמא טמא וקאי. tamei
tamei veka'ei. You are already טמא tamei. at the fullest level. טומאה
וביאה נמי המטמא וקאי. tumah uviah nami hametamei veka'ei. One minute, says
the גמרא, Gemara I don't get it.
So let's get back. You said if you're actively touching and you
touch again, right,
you would not get lashes. So says the גמרא, Gemara but how
is that different than when you walk into a house, right, you
are... hold on, let me just read how תוספות Tosafos reads this
question because it's not so clear what the question is. Hold on
one minute based on תוספות, Tosafos, one minute.
Ah, I'm sorry. So תוספות Tosafos says like this, תוספות Tosafos says
we contrasted טומאה וטומאה tumah vetumah to טומאה וביאה, tumah uviah, right?
We said טומאה וטומאה tumah vetumah you don't get lashes according to
רבא, Rava, טומאה וביאה tumah uviah you do. So what's now the
case that you don't get lashes for טומאה וטומאה tumah vetumah according
to רבא? Rava? You're touching one dead body and you touch another,
you don't get lashes because you're already actively טמא. Tamei. So an
analogous case by טומאה וביאה tumah uviah is I'm carrying this dead
body on my shoulder and I walk into a house, right? I
have the same level with related to מת number one and then
I encounter situation number two. So the גמרא Gemara says so then
why are you חייב chayav in that case? You didn't raise your
level of טומאה, right? If when I'm touching and I touch again
I'm פטור patur because I don't raise my level of טומאה according
to רבא, Rava, then even if I'm touching and I walk into
a house as I'm touching, I shouldn't be I should be פטור.
patur. Right. Now of course right of course what you could say
is that טומאה relates to we could say טומאה relates to the
status and I didn't change my status when I touched another dead
body. ביאה Biah relates to the act of entering and that was
a separate violation. But that's the גמרא's Gemara question. If I'm touching
and I touch again I don't get lashes, why when I'm touching
and I walk in do I get lashes?
What's the conceptual difference as an act between touching and entering? That's
the question.
No, but the prohibition of touching is really not a prohibition of
touching, it's a prohibition of being מטמא. metamei. So then you could
say if it focuses on status, so I didn't do anything to
my status if I was actively touching.
And entering is more of an act?
Yeah, it's ועל כל נפשות מת לא יבא. ve'al kol nafshos meis
lo yavo. The verb is do not enter the פסוק pasuk as
opposed to the verb of לא יטמא. lo yitama. So that's what
you could have said, right? But let's see what the גמרא Gemara
says. Okay, נמי המטמא וקאי. nami hametamei veka'ei. Why should you violate
there if you're actively touching a dead body when you walk into
the house? אמר רבי יוחנן כאן בבית כאן בשדה. amar Rabbi Yochanan
kan babayis kan basadeh. Basically
the answer is, the way תוספות Tosafos reads this answer, it's all
very vague. תוספות Tosafos reads this answer which is like basically like
you're right. If you're actively touching a dead body, it's on your
shoulder and you walk into the house, you would not get another
set of lashes. But when we said you get two lashes for
ביאה biah entering into the house, we meant you weren't touching anything
and you just walked into a house and you got the two
prohibitions at the same time. Okay, and the analogy there for טומאה
that's בבית, babayis, you enter into a house. If you're out in
the field and you touch two dead bodies at the same time,
you're only חייב once, it's one prohibition. Okay? So you're right. If
you're actively touching and you walk into a house you have a
full level of טומאה already present, you would not get another set.
When we said you're חייב twice for entering, it's when you walked
into a house and you got two sets of lashes for that
one act. And the parallel to that of touching two dead bodies
out in the open field you would not get two sets of
lashes. Yeah.
Just out of curiosity, if we're focusing on the נזיר and his
prohibitions of becoming טמא, Tamei, but there's no prohibition for making a
נזיר טמא Tamei.
other than an איסור, issur, right? Right,
I mean by a כהן kohen there's high prohibition about קדושים יהיו,
kedoshim yihiyu, you know, וקדשתו vekidashto that you have to also work
to help protect his טומאה.
Right, and since he is a קדוש?
kadosh? Presumably not. Yes. Okay. Yes.
What is the two transgressions when he enters the house? There's a
corpse in the house, he's not טמא.
Tamei Yeah, one is a prohibition of לא יטמא Lo Yitama and
the other is לא יבוא. Lo Yavo. Those are two separate פסוקים
Psukim and two separate prohibitions.
Going into
the house you become טמא. Tamei Right. And so for the one
טמא, Tamei, it's one act which violates two prohibitions. Do not enter
and do not enter the house, לא יבוא, Lo Yavo, and do
not become טמא. Tamei There's no way to transgress לא יבוא Lo
Yavo without also transgressing לא יטמא, Lo Yitama, but conceptually they're distinct
prohibitions.
Standing over a corpse in a cemetery, that's the same as entering
the house, right? Even though it's not technically like you're on the
grave.
Yeah,
so no, it's a good question. Meaning conceptually we define them as
one as being under an אוהל Ohel and the other is being
מאהיל, Ma'ahil, you know, being like you are tenting over the dead
body. But I but the prohibition of לא יבוא Lo Yavo seems
to be only entering into a house, you know, only a roof
covers the two of you, not that you walk over the grave.
I see.
Right. Under a roof that carries the טומאה. Okay. I mean technically
speaking if he was in a separate room that had a wall
and טומאה wasn't being communicated from one to the other you would
not transgress. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this: כאן
בבית כאן בשדה. Kan Babayis Kan Basadeh. Okay, so I'm reading all
this according to תוספות. Tosafot. It's clear that the גמרא Gemara is
pretty terse. So the גמרא Gemara, continues: בבית נמי כיון דאייל ידו
איסתאב כי אייל כוליה האי טמא הוא. Babayis Nami Kevan De'ayal Yado
Ista'ev Ki Ayal Kulei Hai Tamei Hu.
The גמרא Gemara says like this, I don't get it. By the
house also as soon as you enter in your hand, like if
you're normally walking it assumes I don't know your hand goes in
first, I would have thought your foot goes in first. Anyway, so
as soon as a little part of your body goes in, you
became טמא Tamei, and you do not you don't transgress לא יבוא
Lo Yavo until the majority of your body goes in. That's what
it assumes. It assumes that לא יבוא Lo Yavo you as an
entire person has to have entered the house. So as soon as
you put your foot in, you're טמא Tamei and then you're actively
engaging in the טומאה because you're remain under the same roof. It's
like you're actively touching the dead body. So here I'm טמא, Tamei
I'm still encountering the טומאה and the rest of my person comes
in so I shouldn't transgress, right? Because I didn't do לא יבוא
Lo Yavo until a half second later and at that stage I
had the full level of טומאה.
Well, so that's right. So they're playing with the two פסוקים, Psukim,
one is stated and one is the action is יבוא. Yavo. So
can half of you can your hand be טמא Tamei while the
rest of you is not?
No, all of you is טמא, Tamei, but you haven't been יבוא
Yavo yet. As soon as your hand enter in, all of you
becomes טמא Tamei but you haven't been יבוא Yavo yet. So the
גמרא Gemara says and then when you are יבוא, Yavo, it's like
you're actively touching the dead body already, so I don't get how
you transgress two.
Yeah, they double dip.
So אלא אמר רבי אלעזר, Ela Amar Rabi Elazar, no they're not,
it's a great גמרא, Gemara. they're conceptually distinguished. אלא אמר רבי אלעזר:
Ela Amar Rabi Elazar: צריף ידו, Tzirif Yado, so משום טומאה איכא
משום ביאה ליכא. Mishum Tumah Ika Mishum Bi'a Leka. And if you
just
like stuck your hand in, you would be טמא Tamei without having
entering, although צריף. Tzirif. וצריף גופו, Vetzirif Gufo, if however you had
your hand, you know, sort of connected to your body, flat against
your body, so you walked in like this. Okay? In that case:
טומאה וביאה בהדי הדדי קאתי. Tumah Ubi'a Bahadi Hadadi Kasi. Then it
all comes at the same time. The גמרא Gemara is not going
to be happy, such a fun גמרא Gemara now it's a nice
break from the previous גמרא. Gemara The גמרא Gemara says: האי אפשר
דלא אייל חוטמו ברישא? Hai Efshar Delo Ayal Hotmo Beresha? What do
you mean? Your nose goes in before the rest of your body!
So you are טמא Tamei before you have entered the house, you're
considered having entered the house. Now, the immediate answer I think we
would think is let's say you walk in backwards. So תוספות Tosafot
says no, because since לא יבוא Lo Yavo focuses on the act,
not on the state, if you enter backwards it's שלא כדרכו Shelo
Kedarko and you don't transgress.
Actually this also relates to the whole issue by entering into a
בית מצורע, Beis Metzora, that you're not allowed to enter, right? That
when you enter, not that you're not allowed to but when you
enter
into
the house of a מצורע Metzora, you become טמא, Tamei but there
also it focuses on the act of entering and not like some
idea of like touching and there's definitions of what defines entering there
by a מצורע, so it's just an analogy to think about.
Wait, so תוספות Tosafot says you're not טמא Tamei at all or
just?
No, you wouldn't transgress. You're טמא Tamei. as soon as any part
of your body enters, that's the הלכות Halachos of טומאה. But you
only transgress לא יבוא Lo Yavo when you enter a normal way.
So the גמרא Gemara couldn't say walking backwards. So it says now
you got your nose come in, wait wait let's say the
nose is normal like you know the way you're?
Who knows? Let's keep on going. Okay, there's degrees of normal. Okay.
וצריף גופו, Vetzirif Gufo, it means like your hand is against your
body, that's the way תוספות Tosafot reads it. Okay. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this: So okay, האי אפשר דלא אייל חוטמו ברישא
Hai Efshar Delo Ayal Hotmo Beresha ונחית ליה טומאה, Unehis Lei Tumah,
and as soon as your nose goes in you're טמא tamei and
you don't and you don't transgress לא יבוא Lo Yavo until a
second later. So the גמרא Gemara says: אלא אמר רבא: Ela Amar
Rava: הכניס ידו משום טומאה איכא משום ביאה ליכא. Hechnis Yado Mishum
Tumah Ika Mishum Bi'a Leka. As soon as your hand or nose
or anything goes in, yes you're טמא tamei and you don't have
the איסור Isur of לא יבוא Lo Yavo and presumably then when
you finish entering you don't get lashes because you're fully טמא tamei
and actively טמא. tamei So the גמרא Gemara says אלא אמר רבא
Ella amar Rava הכניס ידו משום טומאה איכא משום ביאה ליכא. Hichnis
yado mishum tumah ika mishum bi'ah lika. As soon as your hand
or nose or anything goes in, yes you're טמא tamei and you
don't have the איסור issur of לא יבוא lo yavo and presumably
then when you finish entering you don't get lashes because you're fully
טמא tamei and actively טמא tamei at that stage. So what's the
case when you get both of them at the same time? So
הכניס גופו בטומאה Hichnis gufo b'tumah so הכניס גופו טומאה וביאה בהדי
הדדי קא אתיין. Hichnis gufo tumah u'bi'ah bahada hadadi ka atyan.
Okay, so but when you go, when you, but when your body
goes in at once, then you get them both at once. But
like what did he say? That wasn't clear. He just said ידו
yado versus גופו. gufo. He didn't give me an answer. He didn't
tell me, you know, how you avoid this problem about the nose.
So it sounds like תוספות Tosafos had a different גירסא girsa of
הכניס hichnis but something like הכסיף, hichsif, which is basically you bent
over. And according to תוספות Tosafos you did the what's that called
when you have to walk under the bar in the limbo?
The limbo.
Yeah like you did the limbo. You went like this. That's שלא
כדרכה. shlo k'darka. Walking backwards is שלא כדרכה. shlo k'darka. Anyway that's
how תוספות... Tosafos... he might have had the גירסא girsa הכסיף גופו.
hichsif gufo. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, right, we're going to
get to that. והא אי אפשר דלא עייל אצבעי דכרעי ברישא. Ve'ha
ee efshar d'lo ayel etzba'ei d'karaei b'reisha. One minute, the fingers of
his foot, his toes went in first. Okay, as soon as one
foot goes in or you know, you're טמא tamei before your whole
body goes in. I guess you could say you jumped in. That
would have been a good answer. Anyway the גמרא Gemara says like
this: ונחת ליה טומאה venachis lei tumah and you already became טמא
tamei before you've entered. So the גמרא Gemara says אלא אמר רב
פפא Ella amar Rav Papa כגון דניכנס בשידה תיבה ומגדל k'gon d'nichnas
b'shida teiva u'migdal
you entered in some type of a box, like you know when
the Chabad house brings in thing one and thing two? Right is
that what he does? He brings in this big box. Anyway ובא
חבירו ופרע עליו את המעזיבה u'va chaveiro u'para alav et ham'aziva
and your friend came and he ripped the top off. I know
David you said last time the Artscroll translated that as he ripped
the bottom off. Right?
You're sitting in a cemetery and
getting it from below.
No, you're getting it from above. פרע מעזיבה, Para m'aziva, the simple
sense is the top. Okay, you rip the top off.
Shomai! מעזיבה m'aziva is the plaster of the roof. Anyway, okay in
that case טומאה וביאה בהדי הדדי קא אתיין, tumah u'bi'ah bahada hadadi
ka atyan, it all comes at the same time. Now תוספות Tosafos
says they have to have warned you in the box and said,
you know, you're not... and you actually have to be helping your
friend, because if your friend does it, you're not to blame, right?
He did it to you. So basically it's more... it's not so
much ובא חבירו, u'va chaveiro, that was just a phrase of ובא
חבירו, u'va chaveiro, but in this case actively they have to warn
you in the box: hey we see you trying to break out
of the box, you know as soon as you do you'll violate.
And you say I don't care and then you break out of
the box. Okay anyway. All right. Okay exactly. Some friend. Okay. מר
בר רב
אשי אמר. Mar bar Rav Ashi amar. Now we get an interesting
twist on this. כגון דאייל כשהוא גוסס. k'gon d'ayal k'shehu goses. He
entered into the house when the person was on... basically you
know... deathbed, death throes. Thank you. So it was clear that he
was about to die, presumably you need that so that the התראה
hatra'ah will see in a minute
how to conceptualize that, but as soon as you the התראה hatra'ah
has to be meaningful. So basically a guy is there and he's
on his death throes, he's going to die any minute and they
say to you: hey buddy, you're a נזיר, you better get out
of here. And he says I don't care I'm going to stay
here, you know this is my friend or this is my father,
I'm going to stay here even you know when he dies or
whatever. And then he dies on you. So at that moment that
he dies, you know you're willingly remaining present. Well presumably גוסס goses
is a חזקה... khazakah... רוב גוססים למיתה. rov gosesim l'misa. But let's
ignore that. Let's assume it's ודאי vadai enough and the act of
staying there he does ביאה bi'ah and טומאה at the exact same
time. Okay. ונפק נשמתיה עד דיתיב u'nafik nishmasei ad d'yasiv and the
טומאה and then the person departs while this guy is remaining there.
דטומאה וביאה בהדי הדדי קא אתיין, de'tumah u'bi'ah bahada hadadi ka atyan,
they come at the same time. And now the גמרא Gemara gets
into an interesting question of is it forbidden for a כהן Kohen
to be in a place where somebody is a גוסס? goses? Very
relevant. Can a person be with a... you know I mean if
it's an immediate family then obviously the person could be מטמא mitamei
to the person as well. But if it is somebody who's not
immediate family, who the כהן Kohen is not allowed to be נטמא
nitma for, can he be with the person up to the last
minute? Okay, so let's take a look.
But if this גמרא's Gemara discussion is about לא יבוא, lo yavo,
how is that person in the room with the גוסס? goses? How
is he... how is he over on לא יבוא?
lo yavo? He doesn't... it's not doing... oh you mean or the
guy breaking out of the box? Because he... no because you mean
at least in the box case there was an act of entering
into the space, here you're already in the space. It's a good
point. It has to read לא יבוא lo yavo as including being
present in the same space. But that's a good point, בא bo
means to enter.
So yeah I guess you're already in the room and then he
dies while you're in the room, it should not have violated...
unless maybe that's part... unless partly that's why it says גוסס goses
because the act of entering retroactively. But then it wouldn't be בהדי
הדדי. bahada hadadi. That's a very good question. That's a very good
question. All right. So the גמרא says like this: תנו רבנן. tano
rabbanan. מהחלו, Me'hechalo,
so this is by a כהן. Kohen. לא יטמא בעל בעמיו להחלו
Lo yetamei ba'al b'amov l'hechalo to desecrate, violate his status. עד שימות,
Ad she'yamus,
that you do not violate, a כהן Kohen does not violate until
the guy has... until he the person that he's in contact with
has died. Okay? Only that would be... he might be reading it
as like חלל, challal, might be a play on words of חלל.
challal. Or it might just mean his status doesn't change until the
guy's dead. Okay. רבי אומר Rebbe omer במותם, b'mosam,
which is by the נזיר. לא יטמא להם במותם Lo yetamei lahem
b'mosam in their death. יטמא במותם... Yetamei b'mosam... אל יטמא להם במותם.
al yetamei lahem b'mosam. I know it says במותם *bemotam* יטמא *yitama*.
It says אל יטמא להם במותם *al yitama lahem bemotam*. Anyway, עד
שימות *ad
sheyamut*.
Okay?
לא יטמא להם במותם *lo yitama lahem bemotam*.
I know it says במותם *bemotam* יטמא *yitama*. It should be יטמא
במותם *yitama bemotam*. Anyway, the point of the same drasha is עד
שימות *ad sheyamut*. It's only a violation once they're already dead. So
מאי בינייהו *mai beinaihu*? What's the difference? אמר רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan.
*amar Rebbi Yochanan* משום דורשי המיתא בינייהו *mishum dorshei hamita beinaihu*. Yeah,
there's no difference. One learns it from this פסוק pasuk. *pasuk*, one
learns it from that פסוק *pasuk*. Okay, just where do you get
it from? ריש לקיש Reish Lakish, אמר *Reish Lakish amar* גוסס goses?
איכא בינייהו *goseis ika beinaihu*. No, the question is, do you violate
even if the guy is about to die? Okay, למאן דאמר במותם
*le-man d’amar bemotam* in their death, עד שימות *ad sheyamut* אין *in*
גוסס goses? *goseis* לא *lo*. Okay, I stepped a line. למאן דאמר
מלהחלו *le-man d’amar melehachelo* אפילו גוסס goses *afilu goseis*. Now, why does
להחלו *lehachelo* include even a גוסס *goseis*? So it could be if
להחלו *lehachelo* because it could if החלו *hachelo* is חלל *chalal* a
corpse, then it shouldn't. But להחלו *lehachelo* is also future-oriented. In and
so to where will be מחלל *mechallel* you, anticipation of, and also
לחלל *lechallel* there could if it’s if it's an abstract concept of
חילול *chillul* of your status which we talk about you know putting
yourself in a risky situation as a type of a חילול *chillul*
of your status. So להחלו *lehachelo* could include the idea of גוסס
*goseis*. איכא בינייהו *ika beinaihu* למאן דאמר להחלו *le-man d’amar lehachelo* אפילו
גוסס *afilu goseis*. I'm sorry. למאן דאמר במותם *le-man d’amar bemotam* עד
שימות *ad sheyamut* אין *in* גוסס *goseis* לא *lo*. Okay, so it
only includes that case. Now we’re not distinguishing, you could distinguish כהן
kohen, *kohen* this and נזיר *nazir* that. We’re just assuming it’s all
the same. ולמאן דאמר מלהחלו *u-le-man d’amar melehachelo* it’s טומאה *tuma*, right?
As opposed to going to a vineyard?
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
To a grave.
Yeah, yeah, there’s all טומאה *tuma*. ולמאן דאמר מלהחלו *u-le-man d’amar melehachelo*
הכתיב במותם *haksiv bemotam*. Again, this גמרא *Gemara* makes it clear that
we're not distinguishing between טומאה *tuma* and נזיר *nazir*. Assuming it’s a
different דרשה *drasha*, what do you do with במותם *bemotam*? If you
already know the idea of until their death or until they're about
to die? מיבעי ליה לכדרבי *mibaya lei le-ki-d’Rebbi* to teach what רבי
*Rebbi* teaches, דתניא *d’tanya*, רבי אומר *Rebbi omer*, במותם *bemotam* אינו מטמא
mitame *eino mitama*, אבל מטמא *aval mitama* בניגעתם ובזיבתם *biniga-atam u-v’zivatam*. That
while a נזיר
*nazir* cannot touch somebody who is dead, he can touch somebody who
is a מצורע *metzora* or זב *zav*. It's only a prohibition of
טומאה *tuma* of touching a dead body not of other טומאות *tumot*
even very weighty טומאות *tumot*. ולמאן דאמר במותם *u-le-man d’amar bemotam* המיבעי
ליה להאי *ha-mibaya lei le-hai*? So the one that says במותם *bemotam*
tells you you have to wait till that it's only a problem
when the
guy is dead, don't you need it for that, to exclude other
טומאות *tumot*? No, סברא הוא להאי סברא *sevara hu le-hai sevara*, excuse
me, you need it you need it for that reason. No, אם
כן לימא קרא במות *im kein leima kra bemot*. If it just
wanted to tell you that it was about טומאה *tuma* of death
and not טומאה *tuma* of others, it could have said in death.
מאי במותם *mai bemotam*? Their death? שמע מינה תרתי *shma mina tarti*.
So it’s one of these things where we claim that there's an
extra phrase, an extra letter, so we learn out number one, only
טומאה *tuma* of corpses is a problem and number two, until the
guy becomes a corpse. שמע מינה תרתי *shma mina tarti*. Until the
guy actually dies. ולמאן דאמר במותם *u-le-man d’amar bemotam* הכתיב להחלו *haksiv
lehachelo*? What do you do with the להחלו *lehachelo* verse, especially if
להחלו *lehachelo* suggests something different, suggests even גוסס *goseis*? No, so the
גמרא *Gemara* says להחלו הכי הוא דאתא *lehachelo hachi hu de-ata*. Here's
what להחלו *lehachelo* is teaching you. במי שאינו מחולל *b’mi she-eino mechullal*
יצא זה שמחולל ועומד *yatza zeh she-mechullal v’omed*. What we said before,
right? להחלו *lehachelo* is a prohibition is only to violate a status.
If you're already violated, your status has been violated, the way we
explained it now is according to רבא Rava *Rava*, you're actively touching
the dead body, then you don't violate again when you touch another
body body body. So the גמרא *Gemara* says ולמאן דאמר מלהחלו *u-le-man
d’amar melehachelo* המיבעי ליה להאי סברא *ha-mibaya lei le-hai sevara*? So the
one that learns it out from להחלו *lehachelo*, how do you learn
this idea that if you're active if you're already status has been
violated you don't transgress again or you don't get lashes again? So
the גמרא *Gemara* says no, אם כן לימא קרא להחל *im kein
leima kra lehachel*. מאי להחלו *mai lehachelo*? Again, one of these plays.
It could have done without the ו *vav*. שמע מינה תרתי *shma
mina tarti*. It tells you two things. Number one, the prohibition of
גוסס *goseis* and number two,
the point that it doesn't apply once the status has been violated.
So the גמרא *Gemara* says okay. מיתיבי *meisive*. I’ll ask from this.
אדם אינו מטמא אלא עד שתצא נפשו *adam eino mitama ela ad
she-teizei nafsho*. A person doesn't cause טומאה *tuma* until they actually the
soul departs. ואפילו מגוייד ואפילו גוסס *v’afilu meguyad v’afilu goseis*. Even if
the person has been you know has been like crucified like he's
and
or he's on his death throes, he's not טמא tamei. *tamei*. So
the גמרא *Gemara* assumed that the one that included גוסס *goseis* literally
thought that a גוסס *goseis* was already מטמא *metamei*. Oh. That's what
the גמרא *Gemara* thought. So now the גמרא *Gemara* no none of
you thought that, but that's what the גמרא *Gemara* does. So now
the גמרא *Gemara* corrects that. The גמרא *Gemara* says no, so the
גמרא *Gemara* says ואפילו ולמאן דאמר מלהחלו *v’afilu u-le-man d’amar melehachelo* הכא
תני דאינו מטמא *hacha sani d’eino mitama*. But if you learn from
להחלו *lehachelo* to include a גוסס *goseis*, it says a גוסס *goseis*
isn't טמא tamei. *tamei* yet. אמר *amar*, you’re right. לענין טמויי *l’inyan
tamuyei* עד דנפיק נפשיה *ad d’nafik nafshieh*. To be טמא *tamei*, of
course, guy has to die. אבל לענין אחלויי *aval l’inyan achluyei* הא
איחלויי *ha ichluyei*. But to violate your status, you violated your status
once you entered the room where he's a גוסס *goseis*. Now this
is an interesting question because because how do we פסקן pasken *pasken*?
Do we פסקן pasken *pasken* the להחלו *lehachelo* version or the במותם
*bemotam* version? Which is a very relevant question of can a גוסס
*goseis* enter a כהן kohen *kohen* enter. of somebody who's not a
relative when the person is a גוסס. The other question is, is
about what do we say in terms of נו, nu, in terms
how much is it really understood to be a biblical violation, it's
the same violation, coming טמא is entering a גוסס? I mean the
גמרא seems to, it learns it from the פסוק. But it's a
little funny that that, really, that's the same violation, entering גוסס? It
sounds more like a דרבנן type of a concern, right? So A,
how do we פסקן pasken and B, what's the level of prohibition?
So if you take a look at תוספות, Tosafot, ומהכא, Umehacha, תוספות
Tosafot says the following, last תוספות Tosafot on the page, שמעינן דכהן
אינו מוזהר על הגוסס דקיימא לן כרבי יוחנן לגבי ריש לקיש דאמר
מוזהר, Shmainan d'kohen eino muzhar al hagoses d'kayma lan k'Rabbi Yochanan l'gabbei
Reish Lakish d'amar muzhar, he really understands it as an איסור דאורייתא.
issur de'oraisa. Nevertheless,
we rule that it doesn't, that we rule like רבי יוחנן. ומיהו
בה״ג גרס אביי במקום רבי יוחנן ורבא במקום ריש לקיש. Umihu Bahag
garas Abaye bimkom Rabbi Yochanan v'Rava bimkom Reish Lakish.
So now you switch the players and רבא Rava is ריש לקיש,
we פסקן pasken רבא Rava. over אביי. Abaye. ולפי זה הלכה כרבא
לגבי אביי לגבי דאביי ורבא פליגי בדרבנן וכו׳, Ulfi zeh halacha k'Rava
l'gabbei Abaye לגבי d'Abaye v'Rava pligi b'drabanan v'chu, etcetera, ואי סתמא הלכה
כרבא אם כן יהא כהן מוזהר על הגוסס. v'i stama halacha k'Rava
im kein yehei kohen muzhar al hagoses. So if you take a
look, so he doesn't know what the answer is, you take a
look at the שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch by the way and the
language of the שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch is, do I have it
up here? No, I don't, hold on. The language of the שולחן
ערוך Shulchan Aruch is,
here, one minute,
where is it? No, no, no.
Ah, here we go.
I think it's שנ״ע. Shin Ayin. Yeah. Okay. מי שנשבר מפרקתו ורוב
בשרו עמו וכן מי שנקרע מגבו כדג אפילו עדיין הוא חי חשוב
כמת ומטמא. Mi shenishbar mafrakto v'rov besaro imo v'chen mi shenikra migabo
k'dag afilu adayin hu chai chashuv kemes umitamei.
That's as the definition of death, which is fascinating in itself on
a, so. But then he says, אבל גוסס ומי שנשחטו בו ב׳
סימנים או פצוע פצעים הרבה וכו׳, aval goses umi shenishchatu bo beis
simanim o patzua p'tzaim harbeh v'chu, it's so tragically relevant to the
events of yesterday, אינם מטמאים עד שתצא נפשם ומכל מקום אסור להיכנס
לבית שיש בו גוסס. einam mitamaim ad sheteitzei nafsham umikol makom assur
lehikanes l'bayis sheyesh bo goses.
So אסור assur is not exactly the same as מוזהר, muzhar, although
with שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch you never know for sure, ויש מתירים.
v'yesh matirim. And the רמ״א Rema says וטוב להחמיר. v'tov lehachmir.
Okay, so it's very ambiguous how אסור, assur, how we פסקן paskens
the גוסס and what level of איסור issur it is. Now what
we did not get a chance to discuss and I'm not going
to try to squeeze it into the zero minutes we have left,
unfortunately I'm going to leave it for שבת, Shabbos, can you guys
give me two more minutes? I just want to talk about, oh
okay, so I just want to talk about, because we started seven
minutes late, I want to talk about how do we פסקן pasken
למעשה lemaiseh about this issue that if a כהן, kohen you're already,
that at most the only thing you get off of based on
this גמרא is if you're actively touching a dead body, right? So
and that's if you're a כהן Kohen to touch another dead body.
So that's what תוספות Tosafot concludes and if you take a look
at תוספות, Tosafot, תוספות Tosafot says like this, מהכא משמע, mehacha mashma,
the earlier מהכא, mehacha, the last of the narrow lines. מהכא משמע
דכהן אסור לטמא, mehacha mashma d'kohen assur litamei, you see this?
The מהכא, mehacha, the last of the narrow lines, the last of
the, right before the lines get middle-sized in תוספות. Tosafot. Okay, you
see the word מהכא? mehacha? מהכא משמע דכהן אסור, mehacha mashma d'kohen
assur, now there's a question of the גרסא, girsa, but it's basically
לטמא לקרובים אף כשהוא מטומא כבר לקרוביו. litamei lakrovim af k'shehu mituma
kvar l'krovav.
Basically the point is a כהן Kohen is there burying his relative
in the cemetery, okay, and he cannot say well I'm already טמא
so I might as well go visit some other graves while I'm
here, okay, and become טמא same day or whatever, no he can't.
דאף כשהוא מחולל ועומד הוא דאף לפי דברי רבא אם פירש אסור
לטמא. d'af k'shehu mechulal v'omed hu d'af l'fi divrei Rava im peireish
assur litamei.
As soon as the guy stops directly being in contact with his
relative that he was burying, he can't, that's it, he can't become
טמא again. שהרי אחר שפירש ממת יילקה על שאר מתים אם יהיה
עמהם, sheharei achar shepeireish mimes yilkeh al shear mesim im yiheiyeh imahem,
he'll get מלקות malkos if he just, you know, is under the
same tree or walks over a grave. So now תוספות Tosafot says
we got a problem cause where's he going to bury his relative?
You bury him in the grave and then you have to get
out of the cemetery. But as you're walking out of the cemetery,
you've left,
you're no longer in contact with that one, so you're transgressing again.
So תוספות Tosafot says, so then תוספות Tosafot says,
וכן שמעתי מאחיו של רבנו, v'chen shamati m'achiv shel Rabbeinu, I've heard
this from like great authorities, לשון ר״י, lashon Ri, שהנזיר
יושב בבית והוא עת כזאת, shehanazir yoshev babayis v'hu eis kazos,
what? No, no, that's a weird גרסא. girsa. There's somewhere else where
he says, one minute, somebody switches the גרסא, girsa, hold on.
That was the earlier תוספות. Tosafot. If you take a look at
ט׳ tes in the הגהות hagahos here at the bottom, the lower
right, it says like this, וכן שמעתי וכו׳, v'chen shamati v'chu, no,
no, no. Somewhere here it says, wait, somewhere תוספות Tosafot said here
that that's why we have to bury the כהנים kohanim bury the
bodies at the edge of the cemetery. Hold on.
Did
I have it? I had it for a moment, wait. שיטת רבנו
Shitas Rabbeinu what?
No. Anyway, I thought I saw it here, but somewhere, I'm sure
it's in another תוספות. Tosafot.
Anyway, somewhere תוספות Tosafot says, I'm just not finding it right now,
that that's why the כהנים... kohanim... They have to be buried right
at the edge of the cemetery so that they as soon as
they're done they don't have a chance of being מטמא to others.
I mean when that doesn't happen, a כהן Kohen basically has to
run out of the cemetery and try to avoid being מאהיל mahil
and being under the same tree and whatever, but basically that's also
why we say that the practice was to bury the מתים meisim
at the edge of the cemetery and have no trees. Now that
is what the תוספות Tosafos says. Now here is the shocker. Comes
along ראב"ד; Ra'avad; all this is very clear, right? We don't have
any possible non-violation except when you are what do you call it?
Except when you are directly in contact with the dead body. Comes
along the ראב"ד Ra'avad and says, everybody ready for this?
Hold on.
Wait, I pressed I'm on the wrong app. I'm going to be
in the right app. Comes along the ראב"ד Ra'avad and says like
this. He says,
this is in הלכות נזיר Hilchos Nazir after the רמב"ם Rambam פסקן
this. He says like this: אמר אברהם עיינתי בשמועה במסכת נזיר, Omer
Avraham i'yanti b'shmuah b'Maseches Nazir, I looked into the סוגיא sugya here,
our סוגיא, sugya, וראיתי דלדעת רב יוסף טומאה וטומאה בחיבורין של אדם
במת אפילו השתרבא, v'ra'isi d'ledas Rav Yosef tumah v'tumah b'hibburin shel adam
b'meis afilu hishtarba, then he goes through the whole סוגיא sugya and
basically what the ראב"ד Ra'avad reads is the following. The ראב"ד Ra'avad
reads that the whole סוגיא sugya we just did about if you're
actively touching then you don't violate again, that was according to רב
יוסף. Rav Yosef. That רב יוסף Rav Yosef who said that you
don't get lashes that you do get lashes by טומאה וטומאה, tumah
v'tumah, he only meant after you took your hand off and touched
again. Okay, but if you're actively touching, you don't get lashes. That
wasn't רבא. Rava That wasn't the lenient position. That was the strict
position. That was רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. רב יוסף Rav Yosef says
if you remove your hand and touch again, you get lashes. While
you're actively touching you don't. רבא Rava, would say even if you
removed your hand and touched again, you would not get lashes. Okay,
so he turns our רבא, Rava, he reads the סוגיא sugya was
not so black and white. What we thought was רבא, Rava, he
reads as רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. The strict position says that you're
only off the hook while you're actively touching. The lenient position says
even after you've removed your
hand. Because you're already טמא. Because you're already טמא. And then he
ends by saying, and listen to what he says. Now you could
say maybe that's the same day. Maybe the next day there's a
consequence like I discussed. And there's a something in מסכת סופרים Maseches
Soferim that says that, but now I'm just going to read you
the last line. So he goes through the whole סוגיא sugya and
then he
says: דכיון דקיימא לן רבא ורב יוסף הלכתא כרבא. d'keivan d'kaima lan
Rava v'Rav Yosef hilchasa k'Rava. Okay, and therefore even if you removed
your hand and touched again you would not get lashes. מעתה טומאה
וטומאה אפילו פירש וחזר ונגע פטור. Me'ata tumah v'tumah afilu peireish v'hazar
v'naga patur. והכהנים בזמן הזה טמאי מתים הם ועוד אין עליהם
חיוב טומאה. V'hakohanim bizman hazeh tmei meisim hem v'od ein aleihem hiyuv
tumah. So nowadays כהנים Kohanim are all טמאי מתים tmei meisim and
if we פסקן like רבא, Rava they're not violating when they come
in contact again with a dead body
even many days later. והמחייב אותם עליו להביא ראיה. V'hamihayev osam alav
l'havi raya. So, okay, that's the
so if you want to well now, the question is does the
ראב"ד Ra'avad say it's totally מותר, muttar, right, or it's פטור? patur?
Some want to say you don't get lashes, but there's still an
איסור דאורייתא, issur d'oraisa, maybe an איסור עשה. issur asei. So there
are people that say all the ראב"ד Ra'avad said is פטור, patur,
you don't get lashes, if you can't be מחייב mihayev them he
never said it was מותר. muttar. Okay, but nevertheless, ראב"ד Ra'avad reads
that what we thought was רבא was lenient position, that was the
strict position. The lenient position would say even if you removed your
hand and that would be very consequential in terms of issues of
טומאת כהנים. tumas Kohanim. So some people want to rely on this
ראב"ד Ra'avad for the question of can a כהן become a doctor
and come in contact with a dead body for the sake of
becoming a doctor, can this ראב"ד Ra'avad be brought into that conversation
as a factor for consideration? Okay, we will end with this.
The strict position say a כהן can never become a doctor?
Well, that's a separate שיעור. shiur. There are other ways of dealing
with it. Yeah, but it's not a distant פיקוח נפש. pikuach nefesh.
All the recordings off? Yes.